<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-27T18:16:53-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jack Roper’s Site</title><subtitle>My personal site. Last updated Nov 25, 2022</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Long Tail of the Apocalypse: World War Z</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/analysis/science-fiction/world-war-z/2022/11/27/book-analysis-world-war-z.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Long Tail of the Apocalypse: World War Z" /><published>2022-11-27T10:41:20-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-27T10:41:20-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/analysis/science-fiction/world-war-z/2022/11/27/book-analysis-world-war-z</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/analysis/science-fiction/world-war-z/2022/11/27/book-analysis-world-war-z.html"><![CDATA[<p>To no one’s surprise, most people on the planet live very different lives, and tend to do a great variety of different things. This seemingly obvious fact very rarely makes it into zombie fiction, where the destruction of the world puts nearly every character into one of only a few career paths. They can be a victim, with no other purpose other than to be saved by someone else. They can be some sort of fighter or scavenger. Maybe a few background characters end up as farmers. You might even end up with a virologist or two. Personalities and goals, of course, are allowed to vary, but the number of viable vocations shrinks substantially when a fictional society collapses. As such, I feel I rarely get to experience the full effect of a zombie apocalypse in fiction. Society is complex and incredibly large: It can’t just all disappear overnight. What happens to the dentists? Presumably people still have teeth. What about the astronauts, the congressmen, the spies? What happens to all the nuclear weapons, all the cities and power plants and damns and bridges when the dead start to rise? Usually, we never get to know. This isn’t bad: Stories necessarily have to focus on <em>characters</em>, not occupational changes across society. If a story’s scope goes too wide, it can’t focus on any individuals, and any character development or emotional attachment becomes nearly impossible. But what if I’ve had enough of the emotional consequences of a zombie apocalypse, and I want to see the societal and economic effects of such an event? Then, the medium I’d be looking for isn’t a story or a novel, but a documentary. And who the hell would write a documentary about a zombie apocalypse that never happened?</p>

<p>Max Brooks would, and I’m glad he did.</p>

<p><em>World War Z</em>, written by Max Brooks, is something that’s completely unique in the zombie fiction genre, as far as I can tell. It treats the zombie apocalypse as a documentarian might, where each chapter is a short interview with a different individual who experienced the apocalypse from a completely different perspective. To name a few different perspectives explored:</p>
<ol>
  <li>The US Vice President, trying to decide if elections can really be held during such a national emergency</li>
  <li>A black-market doctor who does organ transplants</li>
  <li>The chair of the SEC, trying to re-orient the economy around zombies.</li>
  <li>An entrepreneur who sells fake zombie vaccines.</li>
  <li>Astronauts aboard the ISS</li>
  <li>A celebrity’s bodyguard</li>
  <li>A blind man</li>
  <li>A Japanese “otaku”</li>
  <li>A filmmaker</li>
  <li>A sailor in a nuclear submarine</li>
  <li>Head of the CIA</li>
</ol>

<p>And on and on. I didn’t know there were so many bases for Brooks to cover, hitting every nook and cranny of human existence, and infecting it with the consequences of the scenario he’s setup. By doing that, Brooks both encapsulates the sheer <em>scale</em> of the apocalypse, whereas most fiction only shows us it’s effects on a single person and their immediate vicinity, and the rest of the world is written off as “generally dysfunctional but ultimately unimportant”.</p>

<p>Despite it’s wide scope, Brooks still successfully manages to convey a theme throughout the book. As the apocalypse looms and the global pandemic begins, the interviewed individuals frequently ignore warning signs and under-estimate the severity of a walking plague until it’s too late. Most common is the avoidance of personal responsibility leading up to the undead pandemic: A US senator blames his constituents for not supporting anti-zombie measures until it was too late, the CIA head blames congress for not giving them enough funding to deal with the crisis, and a suburbanite blames the government for not protecting them. Even the man who makes fake zombie vaccines blame the FDA for letting him do it, and blames every other investor and politician who funded his operation.  When Brooks succeeds in convincing you that humans will avoid claiming personal responsibility at all costs, suddenly it’s not just plausible that humans would nearly lose against a shambling corpse; it’s inevitable.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You want to blame someone, blame whoever first called it rabies, or who knew it wasn’t rabies and gave us the green light anyways. Shit, you wanna blame someone, why not start with all the sheep who forked over their greenbacks without bothering to do a little responsible research. I never held a gun to their heads. They made the choice themselves. They’re the bad guys, not me. I never directly hurt anybody, and if anybody was too stupid to get themselves hurt [using my fake vaccines], boo-fuckin-hoo.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Still, it’s not all doom and gloom. Brooks doesn’t end the documentary with the death of civilization. Rather, the second half of the book is dedicated to the slow push-back to clear the world of it’s infection. Brooks describes a massive reorganization of society that <em>works</em>, where when humanity is truly confronted with an existential emergency, it doesn’t collapse. Rather, people unite and change and adapt to the new world they find themselves in, rebuilding and reforging a safe world. Brook’s stories of heroism, both military and societal, paint a portrait of a victorious humanity, in contrast to the panic and disappointment he shows humanity to be in the first act of the book.</p>

<p>I don’t view this as contradictory. I think Brooks is trying to prove a point about humankind’s collective reaction to emergencies: That we’re horrible at dealing with things before they become problems, but when faced with existential threats there’s no species more capable of doing the impossible.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Most people don’t believe something can happen until it already has. That’s not stupidity or weakness, that’s just human nature.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When Brooks focuses on the “long tail” of human society, he accomplishes something almost contradictory. He removes any one person from owning the story, but somehow the story is more personal. His scope encompasses nearly the entire planet, but his theme is narrower than a pencil’s edge. It’s a rare accomplishment, and the fact that it’s contained entirely within a genre known for cheap gore, horror, or humorous nihilism makes it shine relative to the competition. He takes this opportunity to leave us with a harrowing warning that made even more pressing given the world’s recent semi-effective response to the COVID-19 pandemic. There will always be emergencies and catastrophes, panics and problems. Each of us is, ultimately, only a single person. What can we do to prevent, or at least mitigate, the next disaster?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You can blame the politicians, the businessmen, the generals, the “machine”, but really, if you’re looking to blame someone, blame me. I’m the American system, I’m the machine. That’s the price of living in a democracy; we all gotta take the rap. “</p>

  <p>“You can’t blame anyone else, … , no one but yourself. You have to make your own choices and live every agonizing day with the consequences of those choices.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="science-fiction" /><category term="world-war-z" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To no one’s surprise, most people on the planet live very different lives, and tend to do a great variety of different things. This seemingly obvious fact very rarely makes it into zombie fiction, where the destruction of the world puts nearly every character into one of only a few career paths. They can be a victim, with no other purpose other than to be saved by someone else. They can be some sort of fighter or scavenger. Maybe a few background characters end up as farmers. You might even end up with a virologist or two. Personalities and goals, of course, are allowed to vary, but the number of viable vocations shrinks substantially when a fictional society collapses. As such, I feel I rarely get to experience the full effect of a zombie apocalypse in fiction. Society is complex and incredibly large: It can’t just all disappear overnight. What happens to the dentists? Presumably people still have teeth. What about the astronauts, the congressmen, the spies? What happens to all the nuclear weapons, all the cities and power plants and damns and bridges when the dead start to rise? Usually, we never get to know. This isn’t bad: Stories necessarily have to focus on characters, not occupational changes across society. If a story’s scope goes too wide, it can’t focus on any individuals, and any character development or emotional attachment becomes nearly impossible. But what if I’ve had enough of the emotional consequences of a zombie apocalypse, and I want to see the societal and economic effects of such an event? Then, the medium I’d be looking for isn’t a story or a novel, but a documentary. And who the hell would write a documentary about a zombie apocalypse that never happened?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quotes by Dana Ballard</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ballard/2022/11/26/dana-ballard-quotes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quotes by Dana Ballard" /><published>2022-11-26T07:41:20-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-26T07:41:20-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ballard/2022/11/26/dana-ballard-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ballard/2022/11/26/dana-ballard-quotes.html"><![CDATA[<p>I took a class during my last semester at UT Austin called “Computational Brain”, thinking that knowing a little bit of computational neuroscience would allow be to tie some ounce of legitimacy to any ideas about the brain I spouted off later in my life. I figured that if I ever got a model to work, I would be able to point to some similar mechanism in the brain, and then say something along the lines of “Look! It’s biologically-motivated!”.</p>

<p>Rather, I ended up in a class with one of the funniest professors I’ve ever sat in with: Dr. Dana Ballard. I loved going to that class, and while I was in it I wrote down the funniest bits and pieces that he uttered, because I thought he was hilarious. Now he’s gone. I’m sure he’ll be remembered for his research and academic legacy, of which I know very little, but I’ll remember him for his great sense of humor and great lectures.</p>

<p>Anyways, here’s the quote list I saved:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I used to go on a lot of dates when I was younger. I wanted to show off, so I just hoped they’d ask a question about the brain I could answer.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Running is like drugs. Half hour in, the chemicals hit, and you’re just gone.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Are you married? No? Then learn to dance. It’ll help you.”</p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>Student: “Do you dance?”</p>
  </blockquote>

  <p>“No, but my wife does.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I’m not trying to get you kids married but you sure need help.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“If you can’t understand women, you’ll spend your life walking the streets crying.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You eat healthy? In Texas? Have you ever had a ribeye steak? No?!? Oh, what a shame.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The dean told me to not talk about politics in my classes because I’m old.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“If I were in hell they’d make me golf.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Well, sharks don’t own property, so I don’t think they’re very smart.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It’s Miller time!”</p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>Class is in silence</p>
  </blockquote>

  <p>“…you know, like a beer. It’s time for a beer. Because class is over. That’s your cue class is over. Go drink something like a college student.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Instead of Miller time, do you all do marijuana instead? Maybe I should end class with marijuana time.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It’s common for children to go through an autistic period around 3 years old and grow out of it”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“This was published by German scientists in 1944. It’s really nice, considering that.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Starbucks time! That’s what I can use.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Student: “Will a different TA grade my papers?”</p>
  </blockquote>

  <p>“Why, do you plan to bribe them?”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I used to go on airplanes and have a competition to get drunk as fast as I could.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“My first job out of college was to test airplane engines. When there was a result that was deemed unsafe I was in charge of erasing the result. A bit of that and I decided… graduate school. No more industry.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ballard" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I took a class during my last semester at UT Austin called “Computational Brain”, thinking that knowing a little bit of computational neuroscience would allow be to tie some ounce of legitimacy to any ideas about the brain I spouted off later in my life. I figured that if I ever got a model to work, I would be able to point to some similar mechanism in the brain, and then say something along the lines of “Look! It’s biologically-motivated!”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In Defense of Optimistic Politics: The Goblin Emperor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/analysis/fantasy/the-goblin-emperor/2019/12/27/book-analysis-the-goblin-emperor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In Defense of Optimistic Politics: The Goblin Emperor" /><published>2019-12-27T22:41:20-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-27T22:41:20-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/analysis/fantasy/the-goblin-emperor/2019/12/27/book-analysis-the-goblin-emperor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/analysis/fantasy/the-goblin-emperor/2019/12/27/book-analysis-the-goblin-emperor.html"><![CDATA[<p>Political intrigue is a classic topic of fantasy novels. Who will betray who? Does the Queen’s servant know about the archduke’s plot to assassinate the second cousin of the third envoy sent to…. and so on and on. Novels that have politics take the forefront usually have a difficult time doing so. One outcome is that the intrigue becomes too hard to follow, with so many gears and inner workings of the court that only the author can fully keep track of them. Most of these types of stories are better suited for television, where you can at least assign faces to names so that their personalities and loyalties don’t get mixed up as easily. The other fate of fantasy-based intrigues is that they usually ditch the intrigue part and eventually focus entirely on the fantasy part. The court is overthrown, and the intrigue is usually revised as morally trivial in the face of bigger, more fantasy-esque issues, such as the rise of some Greater Evil than politics. Robin Hobb’s Assassin’s Quest/Apprentice does this when Fitz is exiled from the court as Prince Regal takes over. Another famous case is Game of Thrones (a gold star in this subgenre) where the political drama of the first few books is ended by Cersei brutally killing her opponents, and the remaining living squabblers of the first few books must focus on the bigger issue of the Targaryen invasion, or the coming Night King.</p>

<p>With that in mind, The Goblin Emperor manages to pull off court drama as interesting without ever deviating from it. In this book, the fantasy part of the book is merely a setting and not a focus, with the spotlight being on the characters. Lore and worldbuilding is mostly irrelevant, something which usually pulls me away from the book itself. You would think (or, at least, I thought) that this meant I would be reading about petty squabbles between nobles. Instead, I read an incredibly heartwarming book about a Ned Stark of the political court – someone who legitimately wanted to do good but leveraged the court to do so.</p>

<p>Through and through, The Goblin Emperor is a feel-good book. Maia, the main character, is thrown into the position of emperor after his father and four older brothers are killed in an airship explosion. Lifted from peasantry, Maia manages to make allies in court simply by being a good and honest person. It’s like what I expected Game of Thrones to be like, until Ned’s head was suddenly removed from his body. Frequently Maia is given the option between the truthful difficulty and the convenient lie. He chooses honestly, <em>always,</em> and his choice of being honest always turns out right in the end. Maia manages to root out corruption in the court, build bridges with enemies, and help out the peasants all in the span of a year. It’s a stark contrast to the high volume of grimdark novels published in the last decade. I found myself expecting that at any moment it would all go wrong – Lord Chavar would finally manage to assassinate him, or his personal guards would betray him. I think the moment when I finally opened myself up to the unabashed hopefulness of the book was when Lord Chavar kidnaps Maia and prepares to kill him. As a final wish, Maia asks to see Idra, Chavar’s son, who would take the throne when Maia dies. Maia intends to come face-to-face with the person who would replace him and to give him advice. To everyone’s surprise, but Idra has no intentions of becoming emperor. Idra stalls long enough to Maia to be rescued, and rather than execute his family, Maia decides to simply exile Chavar, while personally take care of Idra and his siblings.</p>

<p>Now that Maia is in a position of power, he has both the ability and the right to punish those who would do him harm. When a member of his <em>nohechadrei</em>, his personal guard, betrays him, Maia chooses not to kill him. When Maia is betrayed by Chavar and others, he spares the children of the conspirators while exiling the people responsible. When Maia is given the choice of finally having his vengeance against Selethin, the man who frequently abused him as a child, he chooses mercy, even though Maia has every legal (and debatably moral) right to take his vengeance.</p>

<p>So were there any lessons this book? It’s a hopeful outlook on power and the responsibilities that come with it. It preaches that perhaps power doesn’t corrupt. Maybe there are truly good people. Maybe kindness doesn’t always have ulterior motives other than to build a more connected world. Maybe things will just get better if we just <em>be</em> better. With that, I’ll end on a quote from the book:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Never trust a cynic. They justify their bad behavior by assuming everyone does it.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="fantasy" /><category term="the-goblin-emperor" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Political intrigue is a classic topic of fantasy novels. Who will betray who? Does the Queen’s servant know about the archduke’s plot to assassinate the second cousin of the third envoy sent to…. and so on and on. Novels that have politics take the forefront usually have a difficult time doing so. One outcome is that the intrigue becomes too hard to follow, with so many gears and inner workings of the court that only the author can fully keep track of them. Most of these types of stories are better suited for television, where you can at least assign faces to names so that their personalities and loyalties don’t get mixed up as easily. The other fate of fantasy-based intrigues is that they usually ditch the intrigue part and eventually focus entirely on the fantasy part. The court is overthrown, and the intrigue is usually revised as morally trivial in the face of bigger, more fantasy-esque issues, such as the rise of some Greater Evil than politics. Robin Hobb’s Assassin’s Quest/Apprentice does this when Fitz is exiled from the court as Prince Regal takes over. Another famous case is Game of Thrones (a gold star in this subgenre) where the political drama of the first few books is ended by Cersei brutally killing her opponents, and the remaining living squabblers of the first few books must focus on the bigger issue of the Targaryen invasion, or the coming Night King.]]></summary></entry></feed>